Emir Rodriguez Monegal Papers, 1941-1985 (bulk 1965-1968 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
Emir Rodriguez Monegal Papers
1941-1985
1965-1968
C0652
Princeton University. Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
11 linear feet 24 archival boxes
Rodriguez Monegal, Emir, 1921-1985.
The Emir Rodriguez Monegal Papers consists of correspondence, manuscripts of novels, short stories, verse, plays, and essays by others, mansucripts of essays and criticism by Rodriguez Monegal, photographs, and printed and recorded material.
Emir Rodriguez Monegal, literary scholar and biographer, critic, and editor was born in Melo, Uruguay on July 28, 1921, and died in New Haven, Conn. on November 14, 1985. At the time of his death he was Professor of Latin American Literature and Director of the Latin American Studies Council at Yale University. Rodriguez Monegal became in 1945 editor of the literary section of the weekly Marcha. In 1949 he founded the journal Número, which he co-edited with Manuel Claps and Idea Vilariño until 1955. In 1966 he founded and edited the literary and cultural journal Mundo Nuevo (published in Paris until 1969). He was the author of numerous books and articles many of which made important contributions to the understanding of modern Latin American writing, notably among which are El juicio de los parricidas: la nueva generación argentina y sus maestros (1956), Literatura uruguaya del medio siglo (1966), Narradores de esta América (1963; 1969), and El boom de la novela latinoamericana (1972).
Rodriguez Monegal was also know for his literary biographies of Andres Bello (El otro Andrés Bello [1969]), of Horacio Quiroga ( El desterrado: vida y obra de Horacio Quiroga [1968]), of Pablo Neruda ( El viajero inmóvil: Introducción a Pablo Neruda [1966] and Neruda, el viajero inmóvil [1977]), and of Jorge Luis Borges ( Jorge Luis Borges: A Literary Biography [1978]). He also edited critical and literary collections, among which are José Enrique Rodó, 1871-1917 (1963, 1967), El cuento uruguayo: de los orígenes al modernismo (1965), Borges par lui-memê (1970, 1978, Spanish ed. 1983), The Borzoi Anthology of Latin American Literature (with Thomas Colchie, 1977), Pablo Neruda (1980), and Borges, a Reader: A Selection from the Writings of Jorge Luis Borges (with Alistair Reid, 1981).
The Emir Rodriguez Monegal Papers consists mainly of correspondence between Rodríguez Monegal and a wide range of internationally prominent literary figures, scholars, critics, publishers, and academic institutions(much of it relating to Rodriguez Monegal's role as editor and literary critic of Marcha, and Mundo Nuevo(covering mainly the period from 1965 to 1968. The collection includes notes and manuscript and typescript drafts with holograph corrections of essays, lectures, and book reviews by Rodriguez Monegal. Included also are manuscripts and typescripts of poetry, short stories, and novels of authors such as Homero Aridjis, Cecilia Bustamante, Jose Donoso, Luisa Futoransky, Salvador Garmendia, Pedro Salinas, and Severo Sarduy, some of which were submissions by these writers to the aforementioned journals. There is also a large number of tape recordings of interviews, readings, and lectures by Rodriguez Monegal and others.
Miscellaneous and printed material concerns Marcha and Mundo Nuevo (instructions to contributors, payments to contributors, travel and entertainment expenses, etc.) and the International P.E.N. meeting in Bled, Yugoslavia, in July, 1965. There are also copies of book orders placed by Rodriguez Monegal, newspaper and magazine clippings, press releases, and theater and movie programs.
Collection is open for research use.
Audiovisual Materials (Reading Room Access Only): Digital access copies are accessible on a computer in RBSC's reading room. For preservation reasons, physical access to original tapes is restricted.
The papers were purchased from Thomas Colchie and Associates, Inc., in 1986.
Nothing was removed from the collection.
Donoso, José, 1924- -- Este domingo.; Donoso, José, 1924- -- Rie el eterno lacayo.; Latin American fiction -- 20th century.; Latin American poetry -- 20th century.; Latin American literature -- 20th century.; Latin America -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Interviews.; Audiotapes.; Audiocassettes -- 20th century.; Critics -- Latin America -- 20th century.; Novelists, Latin American -- 20th century.; Poets, Latin American -- 20th century.; Latin American literature
- Series 1: Correspondence, dates not examined; 16 boxes
  The bulk of the correspondence comprises the period 1965-1968, and it is arranged alphabetically. Included are letters by Homero Aridjis, Miguel Angel Asturias, Max Aub, Mario Benedetti, Adolfo Bioy Casares, Guillermo Cabrera Infante, Julio Cortázar, José Donoso, Carlos Fuentes, Gabriel García Márquez, Juan Goytisolo, Jorge Guillen, Manuel Mujica Láinez, Nicanor Parra, Nelida Piñon, Octavio Paz, Manuel Puig, Ernesto Sábato, Severo Sarduy, Luisa Valenzuela, Mario Vargas Llosa, and others.
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - A (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Aguirre, Margarita, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Ainsa, Fernando, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Alatorre, Antonio, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Alegría, Fernando, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Alfred A. Knopf, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Alonso, Rodolfo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Alsina Thévenet, Homero, dates not examined; 3 folders (Folder 8-10)
  - Alvarez, Manuel, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Amorim, Enrique, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Amorós, Andrés, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Análisis, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - Anderson-Imbert, Enrique, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Angelo, Ivan, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  - Arias, Augusto, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  - Aridjis, Homero, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 18)
  - Arteche, Miguel, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 19)
  - Asomante, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 20)
  - Asturias, Miguel Angel, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 21)
  - Ateneo Ibero-Americano, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 22)
  - Aub, Max, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 23)
  - Ayala, Francisco, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 24)
  - B (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Baeza Flores, Alberto, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Banks & Miles, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Barea, Arturo & Ilsa, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Bareiro Saguier, Rubén, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Barthes, Roland, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Bastos, María Luisa, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Becco, Horacio Jorge, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Behar, Lisa Block de, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Belitt, Ben, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Belli, Carlos German, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Bellow, Saul, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Benavides, Washington, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Benedetti, Mario, dates not examined; 2 folders (Folder 14-15)
  - Benítez, Fernando, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  - Bianciotti, Hector, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  - Bianco, José, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 18)
  - Bioy Casares, Adolfo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 19)
  - Borges, Jorge Luis, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 20)
  - Borges, Leonor Acevedo de, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 21)
  - Bosch, Juan, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 22)
  - Botsford, Keith, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 23)
  - Boule, Annie, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 24)
  - The British Council, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 25)
  - Bromfield, Louis, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 26)
  - Buitrago, Fanny, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 27)
  - Buñuel, Luis, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 28)
  - Bustamante, Cecilia, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 29)
  - C (General), dates not examined; 3 folders (Folder 1-3)
  - Cabos, Pierre, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Cabral, Manuel del, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Cabrera Infante, Guillermo, dates not examined; 2 folders (Folder 3-4)
  - Cabrera Pínon, Guarany, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Cuadernos Brasileiros, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Cajino Vega, Mario, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Campos, Haroldo de, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Canning House, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Carpentier, Alejo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Carr, Raymond, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Casalduero, Joaquín, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Castellanos, Andrés, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Castellet, José María, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - Castillo, Abelardo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Castillo, Othón, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  - Castro, Sergio de, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  - CCF Publications, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 18)
  - Cea, José Roberto, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 19)
  - Center for Inter-American Relations, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 20)
  - Chocron, Isaac, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 21)
  - Christ, Ronald, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 22)
  - Clemente, José Edmundo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 23)
  - Cobo Borda, Juan G., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 24)
  - Cohen, J. M., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 25)
  - Combie, Elsie, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 26)
  - Commentary, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 27)
  - Conti, Haroldo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 28)
  - Cortázar, Julio, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 29)
  - Cortázar, Mercedes, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 30)
  - Cotelo, Rubén, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 31)
  - Coulthard, G. R., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 32)
  - Coyné, André, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 33)
  - Cozarinsky, Edgardo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 34)
  - Cuevas, José Luis, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 35)
  - Cúneo, Dardo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 36)
  - Cunha, Juan, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 37)
  - D (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Daedalus, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Devoto, Daniel J., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Di Giovanni, Norman T., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Díaz, Jorge, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Donoso, José, dates not examined; 3 folders (Folder 6-8)
  - Draper, Theodore, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - E (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Echegoyen, Maruja, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Edwards, Jorge, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Editions Gallimard, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Editions Universitaires, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Editorial Aguilar, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Editorial Joaquín Mortiz, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Editorial Losada, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Editorial Lumen, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Editorial Seix Barral, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Editorial Siglo XXI, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Editorial Sudamericana, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Editorial Universitaria, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Educación Secundaria, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - Ehrman, Hans, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Encounter, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  - Espinosa, Mario, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  - Espinosa, Enrique, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 18)
  - Estenssoro, Hugo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 19)
  - Eudeba, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 20)
  - F (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Fell, Claude, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Fernández Molina, Antonio, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Fernández Moreno, Cesar, dates not examined; 2 folders (Folder 4-5)
  - Fernández Retamar, R., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Ford, Anibal, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Fraire, Isabel, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Franco, Jean, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Fuentes, Carlos, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - G (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Garcia Márquez, Gabriel, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Ghiano, Juan Carlos, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Gombrich, Ernst H., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - Gombrowicz, Witold, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Goytisolo, Juan, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  - Goytisolo, Luís, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  - Grases, Pedro, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 18)
  - Guelbenzu, José María, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 19)
  - Guido, Beatriz, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 20)
  - Guillén, Jorge, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 21)
  - Gullón, Ricardo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 22)
  - H (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Hanke, Lewis, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Haslund, Ebba, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Harss, Luis, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Hernández, Juan José, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Hispania, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Holder, Roy, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Huneeus, Christián, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - I (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Instituto Latinoamericano de Relaciones Internacionales, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Instituto General Electric, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Instituto Nacional de Cultura, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Inter-American Foundation For The Arts, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Irbi, James E., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - J (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Jaramillo Levi, Enrique, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  - Jelenski, Constantin, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  - Jiménez, Juan Ramón, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 18)
  - Jitrik, Noé, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 19)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 20)
  - Jones, Ernest, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 21)
  - K (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 22)
  - L (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Lafourcade, Enrique, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Lago, Elda, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Laín Entralgo, Pedro, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Lastra, Pedro, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Laughlin, James, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Levine, Suzanne Jill, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Lewis, Oscar, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Librairie Pilote, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Lida, Raimundo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - LIFE en Español, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Lihn, Enrique, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Liscano, Juan, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - López Chuhurra, Osvaldo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - López Páez, Jorge, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Luchting, Wolfgang A., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  - Lynch, Marta, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  - M (General), dates not examined; 2 folders (Folder 1-2)
  - Mac Adam, Alfred J., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Madrid, Juan, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Mafud, Julio, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Magis, Carlos, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Maldonado, Denis M., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Mander, John, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Marcha, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Marichal, Juan, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Martínez Estrada, Ezequiel, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Martínez Moreno, Carlos, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Mejía Sánchez, Ernesto, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Michaux, Henri, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - Milla, Benito, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Moirano, Eduardo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  - Monegal de Rodríguez, H., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  - Monsiváis, Carlos, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 18)
  - Moyano, Daniel, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 19)
  - Mujica Láinez, Manuel, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 20)
  - Muller, Mauricio, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 21)
  - Murena, Hector, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 22)
  - N (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 23)
  - Neruda, Pablo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 24)
  - O (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Oliva, Alberto, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Onetti, Juan Carlos, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Onis, Federico de, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Orgambide, Pedro, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Ortega, Julio, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Oviedo, José Miguel, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - P (General), dates not examined; 2 folders (Folder 1-2)
  - Padilla, Heberto, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - The Pall Mall Press, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - The Paris Review, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Parra, Nicanor, dates not examined; 2 folders (Folder 6-7)
  - Parrilla, José, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Pastori, Aurelio, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Pedreira, Hector, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Pendle, George, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Pereda, Fernando, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Piazza, Luis Guillermo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Pinillos, Manuel, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - Piñon, Nelida, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Pizarnik, Alejandra, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  - Plural, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  - Primera Plana, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 18)
  - Puben, José, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 19)
  - Puig, Manuel, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 20)
  - Pupo-Walker, Enrique, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 21)
  - Paz, Octavio, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Paz, Octavio ( L'Herne), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Q (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Quijano, Carlos, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - R (General), dates not examined; 2 folders (Folder 3-4)
  - Real De Azúa, Carlos, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Recavarren, J. L., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Reyes, Alfonso, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Ríos, Julian, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Rivero, Isel, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Roa Bastos, Augusto, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - The Rockefeller Foundation, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Rodman, Selden, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Rodríguez Alfaro, Hugo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Rodríguez Gómez, A., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - Rodríguez Monegal Family, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Roggiano, Alfredo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  - Rojas, Gonzalo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  - Rosa, João Guimarães, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 18)
  - S (General), dates not examined; 2 folders (Folder 1-2)
  - Sábato, Ernesto, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Saer, Juan José, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Sainz, Gustavo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Salvador, Tomás, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Sánchez, Luis Rafael, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Sánchez, Néstor, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Sarduy, Severo, dates not examined; 2 folders (Folder 9-10)
  - Segovia, Tomás, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Solari, Aldo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Sontag, Susan, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Strausfeld, Michi, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - Street, John, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Sucre, Guillermo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  - Suescún, Nicolás, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  - Sur, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 18)
  - T (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Timerman, Jacobo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Todorov, Tzvetan, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Torre, Guillermo de, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Torre Nilsson, Leopoldo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Torres Fierro, Danubio, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Trajtenberg, Mario, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - U (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Ulcia, Manuel, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - UNESCO, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Uribe, Germán, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Uruguay, Ministerio de Instruccion Publica, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Uslar Pietri, Arturo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - V (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - Valente, José Angel, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Valenzuela, Luisa, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  - Vallejos, Roque, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  - Vargas Llosa, Mario, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 18)
  - Vera Ocampo, Raúl, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 19)
  - Vilariño, Idea, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 20)
  - Viñas, David, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 21)
  - Vitier, Cintio, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 22)
  - W (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 23)
  - West, Anthony, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 24)
  - Wey, Virginia & Walter, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 25)
  - White, Edmund, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 26)
  - Wilcock, Juan Rodolfo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 27)
  - Wilson, Edmund, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 28)
  - X (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 29)
  - Xirau, Ramón, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 30)
  - Y (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 31)
  - Yale University, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 32)
  - Yglesias, José, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 33)
  - Yopo, Boris, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 34)
  - Yurkievich, Saúl, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 35)
  - Z (General), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 36)
  - Zagury, Eliane, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 37)
  - Zani, Giselda, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 38)
  - Zea, Leopoldo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 39)
  - Zona Franca, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 40)